so the cycles per instruction we spent
in the pipeline should be one once we
have filled our pipeline note that we
have billions instructions to process in
a program usually so the first few
cycles are negligible we can just ignore
them and say that in the steady state
we're just finishing one instruction
every cycle is that true however so the
reasons why we don't always get the flow
rate of one are the initial filling of
the pipeline but even with the initial
fill the CPI will get closer and closer
to one as the number of instructions
grows and because we have many many
instructions this is not really a big
problem our CPI could be said to be 1 in
spite of this the CPI in the steady
state is not 1 also because of pipeline
stalls think about for example a car
production line where the first stage is
to install the doors the second stage is
to install front wheels the next stage
is to install the rear wheels and there
are many more stages and let's say that
at some point we have a black car here
with the front wheels already installed
a purple car here waiting to install the
front wheels and the green car here
still without the doors it's installing
the doors let's say that during the
installation of the front wheels here
the Machine damages the wheel so now
what happens is when the production line
can move on because the rear wheels have
been installed on the black car the
black car can move on to the next stage
and it has the rear wheels installed but
we don't want to move the purple car
here because it still doesn't have the
front wheels if we let that happen we'll
end up with a car that has no front
wheels so the purple car will stay in
this install front wheel stage for one
more cycle to have a new set of wheels
installed because the purple car didn't
move on the worker over here is idle
because there is no car to install the
rear wheels in this cycle and because
the purple car didn't move on the green
car whose doors have been installed
cannot move on so we have an idle stage
here - let's say that the wheels are
correctly
stole this time here now the purple car
moves on the next stage of the pipeline
however gets to do nothing because no
car has moved on the green car will now
move here and we will begin a new car
here for installing the doors so the
problem is that when the black car
leaves the pipeline there will be one
car worth of time where we don't finish
a car and only then the purple car will
come so every one of these breaks in the
pipeline that stalled the pipeline it
cannot move on will result in not
finishing a car when a car should have
been finished
if these stalls happen on a regular
basis the CPI will not be one it will be
lower than one for example if every five
cars we have this then really takes six
cycles to finish five cars so the CPI is
six cycles over five cars and we end up
with the CPI of 1.2 not one so even the
steady-state pipeline CPI
will be larger than one meaning we don't
finish an instruction every cycle
because of pipeline stalls so we have
seen how a stall can happen in a car
pipeline because of broken wheels or
something but in a processor pipeline
how can it be that we have a stall so
what goes broken with an instruction